Hello everybody, welcome back to the IELTS Intermediate Speaking Course by PREP.
In today's lesson, I'm going to share with you a very useful
technique called FER, which helps expand our ideas and make our answers longer.
In this technique, after answering a speaking part one question by giving
a general direct answer, we will extend our answer by providing information
from one or more of the following categories.
F is for feeling, E - example, R for reason.
Let's look at an example.
Do you have any hobbies?
First, we provide a direct answer to the question.
I will say that I have a hobby, which is woodworking.
Then we can express our F, feeling.
To be specific, we talk about what the hobby makes us feel.
I will say that this hobby makes me feel energized, and then
I further explain that it helps me relieve stress and gives me a great sense of enjoyment.
Next, I compare the current feeling with the feeling before I started
this hobby to further extend the answer.
It also allows me to use the simple past tense to show the examiner more grammatical structures.
Feeling before, depressed due to having too much on my plate.
I always felt depressed.
Why?
Because I had too many things to do.
Next, let's apply the FER technique to the second question by providing
a general answer and then extending it using an example.
What are the benefits of hobbies?
For this question, I will give a general first.
There are many benefits of having a hobby.
Then, I'll provide an example of a specific hobby and the benefit it has on me.
I'll give you 10 seconds to think of your own example.
10 seconds starting now.
Finished?
Here's my example.
I started playing tennis when I graduated from university, and it helped
me relieve stress after work, improve my physical health, and boost my confidence.
Here, I provide an example in the past to use the simple past tense.
Do you understand better now?
Let's move on to the third question and provide a general and direct answer.
Then expand it by adding R, reason.
Is it harmful to spend too much time on a hobby?
First, I'll answer with a simple yes.
Then I provide a reason why spending too much time on a hobby can be harmful.
I'll give you 10 seconds to think of a reason.
10 seconds starting now.
Have you come up with any reason?
Here's my reason.
Spending too much time on a hobby can be harmful because it
may lead to negligence of work and relationships, which constrain important
connections and affect my professional life.
So, now we've learned an effective technique for expanding our ideas for speaking part one questions.
Now, let's listen to my sample answers and read them out loud.
Do you have any hobbies?
Yes, I do.
Recently, I've tried out a new hobby, woodworking.
I have felt incredibly energized as this past time has helped me
relieve stress and bring me a great sense of pleasure.
In contrast to how I used to feel, often depressed by the
to-do lists that were always growing and the constant sense of having too much on my plate.
Let's pause the video and read out loud the sample answer.
What are the benefits of hobbies?
There are a few perks of partaking in hobbies.
I picked up tennis after graduating from university and has become an
immensely pleasurable task, which helps me relieve stress after work.
Additionally, as a form of workout, it also contributes to improving my
physical health, consequently giving me a tremendous confident boost.
Let's pause the video and read out loud the sample answer.
Is it harmful to spend too much time on a hobby?
Yes, spending an excessive amount of time partaking in a hobby is
correlated to the negligence of other life priorities, such as work and
relationships, which constrain individuals' important connections and professional life.
Let's pause the video and read out loud the sample answer.
Today, we learned the F-E-R technique to expand our answers in IELTS speaking.
After giving our answer, we can add feeling, example, and reason.
Good job, everyone.
Remember to review this lesson and finish all the exercises.
Until next time, everyone.